Guide to the Aleksis Rannit Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Aleksis Rannit papers
1937-1985
GEN MSS 715
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
17.21
(45 boxes)
The papers consist chiefly of subject files maintained by Rannit, dating roughly from the 1950s to the 1980s. The subject files include correspondence, writings, photographs, and printed material that document Aleksis Rannit's life and work as an art and literary critic and Curator of the Slavic and East European Collections for the Yale University Library.
Rannit, Aleksis
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 44 contains restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Tatiana Rannit on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1987.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on microfilm.
Arrangement
The collection is organized under three headings: Index to the Aleksis Rannit Papers, General Correspondence, and Subject Files.
Aleksis Rannit (1914-1985)
Alexis Rannit, Estonian poet and art critic, was born in Kallaste, Estonia in 1914. He emigrated to Germany in 1939, and to the United States in 1952. Rannit worked at the New York Public Library in the 1950s and became Curator of the Slavic and East European collections at the Yale University Library in 1961. Rannit's writings include poetry in Estonian and in English translation, and several works of literary and art criticism. Among his major publications are Akna raamistuses (1937), Käesurve (1945), Suletud avarust (1956), Kuiv hiilgus (1963), Kaljud (1969), Line (1970), Sõrmus (1972), Donum Estonicum: Poems in Translation (1976), Cantus Firmus (1978), and Helikeeli (1982).
Scope and Contents
The papers consist chiefly of subject files maintained by Rannit, dating roughly from the 1950s to the 1980s. Some files (such as those on Lidiia Alekseeva and Vytautas Jonynas) consist entirely or chiefly of incoming correspondence, while others (such as that on M.K. Argus) also include drafts of writings, photographs and printed material by or about the subject. Among the most substantial files are those on Ants Oras and Marie Under, both of which include research material and personal and literary papers (of Oras, Under, and Artur Adson). Some files (such as those on Jacques Hnizdovsky, Vladimir Korvin-Piotrovskii, Dmitri Merinoff, and Andrei Sedykh) include papers that document Rannit's work for Yale University, particularly the acquisition of books, manuscripts and works of art. A few files (such as those on Evgenii Evtushenko and Vera Bulich) are purely subject files and do not include correspondence with the subject. Throughout the collection, correspondence includes some letters addressed to Tiina Vedro. Rannit's writings (filed under Rannit in Subject Files) include holograph and typescript drafts of his poems as well as notes on the translation of his poetry into various languages. His writings also include printed versions of his poems, works of art criticism, and other prose writings.
Acquisition of manuscripts; Acquisitions (Libraries); Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art, Estonian -- 20th Century; Art criticism; Authors, Estonian; Authors, Lithuanian; Authors, Russian; Poets, Estonian; Poets, Lithuanian; Poets, Russian; Librarians; Emigration and immigration; Estonian poetry -- 20th Century; Lithuanian poetry -- 20th Century; Russian poetry -- 20th Century; Estonian literature -- 20th Century; Lithuanian literature -- 20th Century; Russian literature -- 20th Century; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs; Librarians; Adson, Artur, 1889-1977; Alekseeva, Lidii︠a︡, 1909-1989; Argus, 1900-1970; Bulich, Vera, 1898-1954; Yevtushenko, Yevgeny Aleksandrovich, 1933-2017; Hnizdovsky, Jacques, 1915-1985; Jonynas, Vytautas Kazimieras, 1907-1997; Korvin-Piotrovskiĭ, Vladimir Lʹvovich, 1891-1966; Merinoff, Dmitri; Oras, Ants, 1900-; Rannit, Aleksis; Sedykh, Andreĭ; Under, Marie, 1883-1980
- Index to the Aleksis Rannit Papers
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of a typed list of a portion of the contents of the Aleksis Rannit Papers, arranged alphabetically by subject, and including additional detail that is not included in this finding aid. The index was compiled by Aleksis Rannit and Tatiana Rannit.
  - "Catalogue", undated; 4 (Box 1)
- General Correspondence
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  General correspondence consists of correspondence formerly filed by language ("Letters in English," "Letters in Estonian," "Letters in Finnish," etc.). Correspondence is chiefly professional in nature, discussing art, literature, music and literary publications. Some correspondence is more personal, including holiday greetings.
  - "A-I" General Correspondence, 11 (Box 2)
  - "J-R" General Correspondence, 12 (Box 3)
  - "S-Z" General Correspondence, 8 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified General Correspondence, 1948-1977 (Box 4)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 4)
- Subject files
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Subject files consist chiefly of incoming correspondence; some files include writings, photographs and other material related to the person or topic. Some boxes include detailed lists of their contents, compiled by Aleksis Rannit and Tatiana Rannit.
  - Aabel, Roland, 1968-1982 (Box 5)
  - Aavik, Johannes, 1960-1971; 2 (Box 5)
  - Adamovich, Georgii, 1964-1971 (Box 5)
  - Adams, Valmar, 1966-1984; 3 (Box 5)
  - Adson, Artur
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Under, Marie
  - Aistis, Jonas, 1947-1971 (Box 5)
  - Aizenshtadt, Mikhail Konstantinovich
    See: Argus, M.K.
  - Aldanov, M., "Fel'dmarshal," printed version, inscribed to Edmund Wilson, undated (Box 5)
  - Alekseeva, Lidiia
    - Letters from Lidiia Alekseeva to Aleksis Rannit, 1960-1980; 3 (Box 6)
    - Writings of Lidiia Alekseeva, 1968, undated (Box 6)
  - Alon, Susan, undated (Box 6)
  - Annist, August, 1965-1974 (Box 6)
  - Anstey, Olga, 1979-1983, undated (Box 6)
  - Ariste, Paul, 1969-1980 (Box 6)
  - Argus, M. K.
    - Letters from M.K. Argus to Aleksis Rannit, 1961-1970 (Box 6)
    - Incoming correspondence of M.K. Argus, 1950-1969; 2 (Box 6)
      Correspondence relates chiefly to M.K. Argus's column in Novoe Russkoe Slovo.
    - Family correspondence, 1909-1923; 2 (Box 7)
    - Writings and family papers of M.K. Argus, 1916-1952, undated; 3 (Box 7)
      Includes a notebook labeled "Poems 1916-1920." Some writings are unidentified and may not be authored by M.K. Argus. Also includes writings of family members, such as a notebook labeled "mother's notebook."
    - Papers of Aleksis Rannit relating to M.K. Argus, 1969-1972; 2 (Box 7)
      Includes letters to Rannit about Argus and clippings about Argus.
  - Asi, Harri and Silvi, 1957-1980 (Box 7)
  - Aspel, Alexander, 1949-1974; 2 (Box 7)
  - Ast, Karl, 1966-1970 (Box 7)
  - Bal'mont, Konstantin, 1937-1978, undated; 2 (Box 8)
  - Baltimore, 1973-1976 (Box 8)
  - Banerjee, Ron, 1974-1983 (Box 8)
  - Barka, Wasyl, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
  - Bauermeister, Christiane, 1979, undated (Box 8)
  - Bedregal, Yolanda, 1960-1983 (Box 8)
  - Belinkov, Arkadii, 1969-1971, undated (Box 8)
  - Berberova, Nina
    - Letters from Nina Berberova to Aleksis Rannit and Tatiana Rannit, 1961-1982; 2 (Box 8)
    - Other papers relating to Nina Berberova, 1963, undated (Box 9)
  - Beresov, Rodion, 1969 (Box 9)
  - Betaki, Vasilii and Violetta Iverni Betaki, 1977-1981 (Box 9)
  - Books Abroad, 1962-1966 (Box 9)
  - Bowlt, John E., 1979-1982 (Box 9)
  - Brodsky, Joseph, 1972-1980 (Box 9)
  - Brown, Francis, 1969-1976 (Box 9)
  - Brown, Spencer, 1978-1983 (Box 9)
  - Brush, Daniel, 1975-1980 (Box 9)
  - Bulich, Vera, 1934-1964, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Burliuk, David, 1961-1967 (Box 9)
  - Cargas, Harry James, 1975-1977 (Box 9)
  - Charchoune, Sergei, 1949-1980 (Box 9)
  - Chinnov, Igor', 1967-1979, undated (Box 9)
  - Chor, Olga, 1961-1971 (Box 9)
  - Christian Science Monitor, 1967-1976 (Box 10)
  - Corman, Cid and Shizumi, 1971-1980 (Box 10)
  - Dobujinsky, Vsevelod and Mstislav, 1975-1980 (Box 10)
  - Ekbaum, Salme, 1966-1976 (Box 10)
  - Elinson, Henry, 1975-1978; 3 (Box 10)
    Includes photographs of drawings by Elinson.
  - Elizabeth Press
    See: Weil, James L./ Elizabeth Press
  - Eller, Helmi, 1972-1984 (Box 10)
  - Esop, Lilian, 1973-1982 (Box 10)
  - Estam, H., 1971-1981 (Box 10)
  - Evtushenko, Evgenii, 1963-1972 (Box 10)
  - Filipoff, Boris, 1963-1983 (Box 11)
  - Fotiev, Father Kirill, 1973-1982 (Box 11)
  - Frederick Ungar Publication Co., 1980-1984 (Box 11)
    See also: Klein, Leonard S.
  - Gabo, Naum, 1975-1981 (Box 11)
  - Galdikas, Adomas, 1945-1966, undated (Box 11)
  - Gardner, Isabella, 1976-1981 (Box 11)
  - George, Emery, 1966-1982; 3 (Box 11)
  - Gippius, Zinaida, undated (Box 11)
  - Gira, Vytautas, 1971-1978 (Box 11)
  - Glassgold, Peter, 1971-1983 (Box 11)
  - Grabar', Oleg, 1971, undated (Box 12)
  - Grabbi, Hellar, 1965-1968 (Box 12)
  - Grünthal, Ivar, 1957-1964; 1 folder (Box 12)
  - Guerra, René, 1975-1982 (Box 12)
  - Gul', Roman, 1957-1982 (Box 12)
  - Hasty, Christopher, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
  - Helbemae, Gert, 1970-1976 (Box 12)
  - Hnizdovsky, Jacques, 1976-1984; 3 (Box 12)
  - Hollerbach, Serge, 1969-1980, undated (Box 12)
  - Il'inskii, Oleg, 1969-1982 (Box 13)
  - Ivannikova, Lidiia
    See: Alekseeva, Lidiia
  - Ivanov, Dmitrii, 1965-1982 (Box 13)
  - Ivanov, Georgii, undated (Box 13)
  - Ivanov, Viacheslav
    - Photographs of Viacheslav Ivanov, Konstantin Bal'mont and others (reproductions), undated (Box 13)
    - Writings of Rannit about Ivanov, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 13)
    - Other papers relating to Viacheslav Ivanov, 1964-1982, undated; 5 (Box 13)
  - Ivask, Iurii, 1961-1980; 6 (Box 14)
  - Ivask, Ivar, 1951-1984 (Box 14)
  - Jakobson, Roman, 1966-1981 (Box 14)
  - Jänes, Henno, 1967-1969 (Box 14)
  - John, Archbishop of San Francisco, 1963-1966 (Box 14)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1973-1981 (Box 14)
  - Jonynas, Vytautas K., 1950-1979 (Box 14)
  - Jürma, Mall, 1961-1981 (Box 15)
  - Kangro, Bernard, 1950-1981; 2 (Box 15)
  - Karlinskii, Semen, 1965-1980 (Box 15)
  - Klein, Leonard S., 1979 (Box 15)
  - Klenovskii, Dmitrii, 1960-1965, undated (Box 15)
  - Koks, Endel, 1946-1951 (Box 15)
  - Kompus, Hanno, 1949-1976 (Box 15)
  - Kõressar, Viktor, 1962-1982 (Box 15)
  - Korvin-Piotrovskii, Vladimir, 1971-1979 (Box 16)
  - Kralin, Mikhail, 1970-1973 (Box 16)
  - Krants, Eduard, 1966-1972 (Box 16)
  - Kuz'minskii, Konstantin K., 1980-1984 (Box 16)
  - Kuznetsova, Galina, 1962-1974 (Box 16)
  - Landsbergis, Algirdas, 1966-1976 (Box 16)
  - Laughlin, James, 1971-1984; 5 (Box 16)
  - Lauwers, Helene, 1980-1982 (Box 16)
  - Lehiste, Ilse, 1965-1981 (Box 16)
  - Leitch, Vincent B., 1975-1983, undated; 3 (Box 17)
  - Lepiksaar, Johannes, 1965-1975 (Box 17)
  - Liebaers, Herman, 1978-1983 (Box 17)
  - Lipchitz, Jacques, 1954-1961 (Box 17)
  - Lozoraitis, Stasys, 1946-1966 (Box 17)
  - Luts, Karin and Peeter Arumaa, 1952-1982 (Box 18)
  - Lüüs, Aadu, 1964-1966 (Box 18)
  - Lyman, Henry
    - Letters from Henry Lyman to Aleksis Rannit, 1968-1975, undated (Box 18)
    - Writings, including English translations by Lyman of Rannit's poetry, 1970-1977; 3 (Box 18)
  - Mänd, Ewald, 1957-1982 (Box 18)
  - Markov, Vladimir, 1961-1981 (Box 18)
  - Masing, Uku, 1968-1982 (Box 18)
  - Marchenko, Nikolai
    See: Morchen, Nikolai
  - McMath, Michael, 1980-1983 (Box 18)
  - Merinoff, Dmitri, 1962-1983; 3 (Box 19)
  - Mickiewicz, Denis and Ellen, 1966-1981, undated (Box 19)
  - Mickeiwicz, Ekaterina, 1968-1976 (Box 19)
  - Miłosz, Czesław, 1964-1981 (Box 19)
  - Morshen, Nikolai, 1976-1981 (Box 19)
  - Nartsissov, Boris, 1972-1982; 2 (Box 19)
  - New Directions
    See: Glassgold, Peter and Laughlin, James
  - New York Times Book Review
    See: Brown, Francis
  - Odoevtseva, Irina, 1964-1969, undated (Box 20)
  - Oinas, Felix, 1959-1981 (Box 20)
  - Oja, Hannes, 1966-1980 (Box 20)
  - Oras, Ants
    - Letters from Ants Oras to Aleksis Rannit, 1948-1980; 3 (Box 21)
      Includes manuscript and typescript poems.
    - Other correspondence related to Ants Oras, 1963-1976 (Box 21)
      Copies of A. Rannit to Ivar Ivask
      Copies of A. Rannit to President, English P.E.N.
      Copies of Edgar Saks to A. Oras
      A. Rannit to A. Oras
      Heimito von Doderer to A. Oras
      Timo Tinsauer and Keijo Incmonen (Finnish P.E.N.) to A. Oras
      A. Rannit to W. B. Fleischman
      W. B. Fleischman to A. Rannit
      A. Rannit to Luna Wolf
      Luna Wolf to A. Rannit
      Mati Hint to A. Rannit
      Hele Lüüs to A. Rannit
      Livia Oras to A. Rannit
      J. Wayne Reitz to A. Rannit
      René Wellek to A. Rannit
      Joan Phvel to I. Rebane
    - Writings of Ants Oras, 1957, undated (Box 21)
      Translations of poems into German and English, manuscript
      Acht estnische Dichter, draft with annotations of A. Oras, typescript
      A. Oras, "Asta Willmann," manuscript (copy)
      A. Oras, "A Few Facts Illustrating the Attitude of the Writers in Occupied Estonia Towards Those Abroad," typescript (copies)
      "Gustav Swits and European Symbolism"
      "On Critics and Criticism"
      "Praegune Alver"
      "Report on the Scholar Qualifications of the Applicants for the Chair of Aesthetics and Modern Literature at the University of Helsinki"
    - Material about Ants Oras, 1962-1982, undated (Box 21)
      A. Rannit, "An Aspect of A. Oras-A Literary Critic Writing in Estonian," typescript, 1982
      A. Rannit, "A. Oras Seen as a Literary Critic Writing in Estonian," 5 versions, typescript, annotated, 1972
      Clippings and typescripts by A. Rannit about A. Oras
      Clippings about A. Oras, including obituaries, reviews, articles by Johannes Kaup, Olev Parlo, Harald Rauchsepp, Linda Raun, Asta Willmann
      A. Raun, "Translator and/or Poet?," typescript
  - Pakhmuss, Temira, 1977-1983 (Box 22)
  - Panin, Gennadii, 1965-1980; 4 (Box 22)
  - Parlo, Olev, 1958-1978 (Box 22)
  - Parrat, Anne, 1976-1979 (Box 22)
  - Pasternak, Boris and Lidiia, 1959-1962 (Box 22)
  - PEN Club, 1949-1977; 2 (Box 22)
    Includes a 1949 photograph of Stephen Spender.
  - PEN Club (continued), 1978-1981 (Box 23)
  - Pereleshin, Valerii, 1970-1979; 5 (Box 23)
  - Petravičius, Viktoras, 1948-1963 (Box 24)
  - Plotnitskii, Arkadii, 1977, undated (Box 24)
  - Puhvel, Joan, 1962-1975 (Box 24)
  - Radauskas, Henrikas, 1947-1969, undated (Box 24)
  - Raila, Bronys and Danuta, 1949-1980 (Box 24)
  - Rais, Emmanuel, 1964-1971 (Box 24)
  - Rannit, Aleksis
    - Biographical research material about Rannit, 1979-1984; 2 (Box 24)
    - Forma Estonica: organizational materials, undated (Box 24)
    - Biographical research material about Rannit, 1948-1978, undated; 5 (Box 25)
    - Biographical research material about Rannit (continued), 1949-1980, undated; 6 (Box 26)
      Clippings, letters, publications and notes by and about Aleksis Rannit.
    - Biographical research material about Rannit (continued), 1971-1979, undated; 3 (Box 27)
      Clippings, photographs, publications and notes by and about Aleksis Rannit.
    - Invention and Tradition, correspondence, proofs, drafts and related material, 1979-1980; 6 (Box 28)
    - Poems of Aleksis Rannit in Estonian, drafts, clean copies (holograph, typescript, and typescript carbon) and printed versions, 1958-1979, undated (Box 29)
    - Poems of Aleksis Rannit, English translations by various translators, manuscript, typescript and printed versions (including copies), 1962-1976, undated (Box 29)
    - Poems of Aleksis Rannit, German translations by various translators, manuscript and typescript (including copies), undated (Box 29)
    - Poems of Rannit, Aleksis, Russian translations by various translators, typescript and manuscript (including copies), 1961-1978, undated; 3 (Box 29)
    - Poems of Aleksis Rannit, translations into various languages, manuscript and typescript (including copies), 1974-1977, undated (Box 29)
    - "Almar Adams: An Estonian Mannerist Poet," notes and draft, typescript, 1968-1981, undated (Box 30)
    - "Kritijonas Donelaitis and Lithuanian Poetry," draft, typescript, corrected, 1960s (Box 30)
    - Mikalojus Konstantinas Čiurlionis, Lithuanian visionary painter, proofs, circa 1984 (Box 31)
    - Mikalojus Konstantinas Čiurlionis, Lithuanian visionary painter, drafts, typescript, annotated (copy), circa 1984; 3 (Box 31)
    - Mikalojus Konstantinas Čiurlionis, Lithuanian visionary painter, notes, circa 1984 (Box 31)
    - "Čiurlionis: In Search of His Philosophical Background," draft, typescript (copy), circa 1984 (Box 31)
    - "Time in Čiurlionis: Observing the hundredth anniversary of his birth," draft, typescript, circa 1984 (Box 31)
    - "Symbolization in Čiurlionis," draft, typescript, circa 1984 (Box 31)
    - "Touching the Currents of the Modernist Movement" draft, typescript, circa 1984 (Box 31)
    - "Select Bibliography" (on Čiurlionis) draft, typescript, circa 1984 (Box 31)
    - Correspondence about Čiurlionis, 1974-1982 (Box 31)
    - Other material about Čiurlionis, including articles by Aleksis Rannit and research material, 1968-1982, undated (Box 31)
    - Writings in English, typescripts and printed versions (including copies), 1948-1960 (Box 32)
    - Writings in English, typescripts, typescript carbons and printed versions, 1961-1973 (Box 32)
    - Writings in English, typescript carbon and printed versions (including copies), 1974-1976 (Box 32)
    - Writings in English, typescripts and printed versions (including copies), 1977-1980 (Box 32)
    - Writings in English, typescripts and printed versions (including copies), 1981-1982 (Box 32)
    - Writings in English, typescripts and printed versions (including copies), 1983-1984 (Box 32)
    - Writings in languages other than English, drafts, typescript, before 1947 (Box 32)
      "Finnische Architektur." Unpublished article written for Das Kunstwerk, typescript, annotated, [early 1950's?]
      "Malestusvork." Postcard: Poem set to music by A. Meigo, undated
      "Auväärne Opetaja Aavel, lugupretaueid ja armsad kaasmaalased," manuscript, undated
      "Märkus Hans Tsirgu graafika kohta," typescript (copy), annotated
      "V.K. Jonynui 50 metu," typescript
      "Vytautas Kasiulis" (in German), typescript, undated
    - Writings in languages other than English, printed versions, 1935-1946 (Box 32)
      "Uenüto kirjandusklubi tegelasi pildis ja epigrammes." Film ja Elu (Tallinn), 3 versions (copies), 1935
      Vokonnom perepldte. Akademiia Soiuz Ob'edinennykh Iskusstv (Tallinn), title page (copy), 1938
      "Estonskie poety nashikh dnei." Vitiaz: sbornik literatury, iskusstva, nauki i obshchestvennoi zhizni (Tallin), printed version (copy), 1939
      "Goethes muzieful isigijo V. K. Johnyno raiziniu kolekcija." Lietuviai (Berlin) no. 12, printed version (copy), 1944
      Edm. Strazdas [pseudonym of A. Rannit], "Vieneri metai be Jurgio Baltrusaucio," Lietuviai (Berlin) no. 9, printed version (copy), 1945
    - Writings in languages other than English, drafts and printed versions, 1947 (Box 32)
      Copy: "Adomas Galdikas." Kauge Kodu (Augsburg) 1/2 (1947) pp. 10-1
      Clipping: "Picasso näitusel." [poem] Kauge Kodu (Augsburg) 1/2 (1947) p. 21
      Clipping: "Boris Vilde." [poem] Kauge Kodu (Augsburg) 10/11 (1947) p. 40
      "V.K. Joynas," 2 versions, typescript, annoatated
      Copy: Eduard Wiiralt. Exhibition catalog. Fribourg: Musée des Augustins, 1947
    - Writings in languages other than English, printed versions, 1948 (Box 33)
      Copy: "Adomas Galdikas." Galdikas, Jonynas, Bakis: Ausstellung der litauischen künstler. Exhibition catalog. Baden-Baden: Kurhaus Baden-Baden, 1948.
      Annotated clipping: "Intiimne kustikiri Pariisist." Eesti Rada (Augsburg) in 2 parts. 20 Aug 1948
      Clipping: "Eduard Wiiralt." Aidai, no 14 (1948) pp. 206-9
      Petravicius, die 'Dainos' und die seele der litauer. Freiburg-im- Breisgau: Verlag Erwin Burda, 1948
    - Writings in languages other than English, printed versions, 1949 (Box 33)
      Clipping: "Marie Under-didziojo estu pete." Musu Kelias, 26 February 1949
      Annotated clipping: "Adomas Galdikas." Viltis (Tübinger) no. 1 (1949)
      Copy: Tre Incisori Baltici Exhibition catalog. Rome: Calcografia Nazionale, 1949
    - Writings in languages other than English, drafts and printed versions, 1950 (Box 33)
      Alfonsas Krivickas. exhibition brochure. Fribourg: Institut Français, 3-19 Jun 1950
      Clipping: "Runon Silta" [four poems] translated by Viljo Kajava. Kiva Taidelehti 5 (1950) pp. 16-7
      Clipping: "R. M. Rilkes Franzözisches Erlebnis." Das Buch, vol. 12, no 2 (1950) pp. 20-37 German
      "Der dritte Weltkongress der Kunstkritiker." Das Kunstwerk, vol 4, no 6 (1950) pp 64-67, typescript
      Copy: "Maarja Emalikkus." [poem] Kirikuleht (Estonian Evangelical Lutheran Bulletin) no. 1 (37) Dec 1950 p. 10 Estonian
    - Writings in languages other than English, drafts and printed versions, 1951 (Box 33)
      Annotated typescript: "Allocution de M. Alexis Rannit, Délégué officiel de l'Estonie (en exil) au Congrès International des PEN-clubs." Lausanne, 28 Jun 1951
      Clipping: "Dailininko V.K. Jonyno kuryba trmty." Mintis (28 Nov 1951)
      Clipping: "Gespräch mit Clara Rilke." Die Neue Zeitung (28 Dec 1951)
    - Writings in languages other than English, printed versions and drafts, 1952 (Box 33)
      Clipping: "Paul Valéry." Välis Eesti (Stockholm), undated
      2 annotated TSs: "Die Freundschaft beginnt erst nach dem Abschied." Schri Kunst schri: ein Almanach alter und neuer Kunst. Baden-Baden: W. Klein, 1952. pp. 28-33
      Clipping: "Rilke et l'art slave." trans. from the German by Gerhard Marcks. Allemagne d'aujourd'hui, 2 (Mar-Apr 1952) pp. 80-90
      Clipping: "Chartre'i katedraal" and "September." Meie Tee (New York) 22 no 3 (1952) pp 40-1
      Clipping: "Balti kontserdi ümber." VES no 40, 4 Oct 1952 n.p. Estonian
      Copy: "Värsse taidearmastaja päevikust." [two poems: "Soprus a la Gainsborough" and "Kuupaisteline soprus"] Kodukolle, no 12 (1952) p. 12 Estonian
    - Writings in languages other than English, printed versions, 1953 (Box 33)
      Copy: "Vytautas Kasiulis." Santarvé (London) no 1 (6) (1953) p 31 Lithuanian
      Clipping: "Vestlus Marie Underiga." Kodukolle, no 3 (Mar 1953) pp 2-4 Estonian
      Clipping: "Adomas Galdikas: Dailininko Artejancios sukakties proga." Draugas (Chicago) 29 Aug 1953 pp 1-2 4 pp Lithuanian
      Clipping: "American Artist aus Wuppertal." Die Neue Zeitung (München) 9 Feb 1953 German
      Clipping: "Apie antana skema ir apie nenormaluji mena." Vienybe, 1953 Lithuanian
    - Writings in languages other than English, printed versions, 1954 (Box 33)
      Clipping: "Viimne kiri Eduard Wiiraltile." VES, 21 Jan 1954, Estonian
      Copy: Eduard Wiiralt. Exhibition catalog. New York: Estonian House, 16-25 Apr 1954. Estonian
      Clipping: "Jonynas ir Galdikas." Vienybe. 11 Jun 1954 n.p. Lithuanian
      Clipping: "Marie Underi kangelaslik pessimism." VES, no. 24 (17 Jun 1954) Estonian
      Clipping: "Protestantai turi tobula barokini mena." Liasvoji Lietuva (Chicago) 40 (212) (8 Oct 1954) p. 2 Lithuanian
      Clipping: "Jacques Lipshits'o paroda moderninio meno muziejuje." Vienybe [1954] p. 3 Lithuanian
      Clipping: "Adomas Galdikas- klajunas audringame vejuje." Vienybe, [1954] Lithuanian
      Clipping: "Ilmar Laaban ja Eduard Wiiralt." VES, no 3 (1954) pp 4, 10 Estonian
    - Writings, printed versions, 1955 (Box 33)
    - Writings, printed versions, 1956-1958 (Box 33)
    - Writings, printed versions, 1959-1960 (Box 33)
    - Writings, printed versions, 1961-1964 (Box 33)
    - Writings, printed versions and typescript, 1965-1968 (Box 33)
    - Writings, printed versions, 1969-1970 (Box 33)